Inventory of the Offley Family Papers 1826-1916
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Offley Family Papers 1826-1916
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2008.164
0.60
76 items
This collection details the history of the Offley Family from 1826 to 1916 through correspondences, diaries, photographs and personal effects. Its creators include multiple generations of Offleys and their associates. The papers provide insight into the daily life of the era as well as major geopolitical events such as the Greek War of Independence, the Spanish-American War, the Philippine-American War, the 1906 San Francisco Earthquake, and World War I. Many of the Offleys served in the United States armed forces. The collection also includes photographs of individuals unrelated to, but, of the same era as, the Offley Family.
Offley, John Holmes, 1802-1845; Corr, L.P.; Hobson, R.P.; Offley, Cleand Nelson, 1869-1930; Offley, Edward Murray; Offley, John Marbury, 1877-1932; Offley, Robert S.; Priestly, Deborah Heaton Remsen, 1801-1887 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 05/05/2008.
Biographical Note
John Holmes Offley, the son of David Offley and Mary Ann Greer Offley, was born at Brooke Court-House, Virginia on 13 October 1802. Educated in Philadelphia, he first traveled to Smyrna (Izmir), Turkey in 1815 where his father, David Offley, had established the first American commercial firm, Woodmans and Offley, in the Levant. John Holmes Offley later entered into a commercial partnership at Trieste with his brother Richard Jones Offley (Richard & John Holmes Offley Co.). He later served as a ship chandler, contracted to provide provisions for the American squadron then stationed in the Mediterranean. John Holmes Offley returned to the United States with his family in 1835. He served, for a time, as the Inspector of Customs for the port of New York City. He moved to Georgetown in Washington, D.C. in 1838. After serving on special assignment for the U.S. War Department, he was appointed as Corresponding Clerk in the U.S. War Department, and later saw service as the Acting Chief Clerk of the U.S. War Department. He served as vestryman for St. Johns Episcopal Church of Georgetown from 1840 until the time of his death. It was at that church that he married Catherine Van Rensselaer Heaton (1806-1887) on 22 September 1823. John Holmes Offley died on 20 December 1845. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/John Holmes Offley.
Scope and Contents
This collection details the history of the Offley Family from 1826 to 1916 through correspondences, diaries, photographs and personal effects. Its creators include multiple generations of Offleys and their associates. The papers provide insight into the daily life of the era as well as major geopolitical events such as the Greek War of Independence, the Spanish-American War, the Philippine-American War, the 1906 San Francisco Earthquake, and World War I. Many of the Offleys served in the United States armed forces. The collection also includes photographs of individuals unrelated to, but, of the same era as, the Offley Family.
Arrangement of Materials
This collection is arranged into twelve series centered around creators. Series One through Five detail the correspondences, diaries, photographs, and personal effects of J.H. Offley, R.S. Offley, C.N. Offley, and E.M. Offley. E.M. Offley's papers comprise the bulk of the collection. Series Six covers the diary of Deborah H.R. Priestly, a relative of the Offleys. Series Seven examines the diary of L.P. Corr, an associate of the Offleys. Series Eight consists of a correspondence between R.P. Hobson and an unspecified Offley. Series Nine contains photographs of the Young Family. Series Ten includes a photograph of Cleland Kinloch Nelson. Series Eleven consists of two photographs ascribed to Herman Schreier. Series Twelve consists of papers and photographs with unknown creators.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs
Geographic Name:
California--History--1850-1950.; Greece--History--War of Independence, 1821-1829
Topical Term:
Diplomatic and consular service.; Philippines--History; Spanish-American War, 1898; United States. Army--Appointments, promotions, salaries, etc.; United States. Navy--History--19th century.; United States. Navy--History--20th century.; World War, 1914-1918.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- J.H. Offley, 1826-1842; id45080
  - Correspondences, 1826-1942; id45081 (Sub-series 1)
    - December 1826- June 1830, id45078 (Sub-series 1, Folder 1)
    - August 1833-February 1842, id45079 (Sub-series 1, Folder 2)
  - Documentation, 1829-1832; id45082 (Sub-series 2)
    - Offley Family, 1829-1832; id45083 (Sub-series 2, Folder 3)
      - Baptismal Record, May 23, 1829; id45084 (Sub-series 2, Folder 3)
      - Diplomatic Nomination, March 21, 1832; id45085 (Sub-series 2, Folder 3)
    - Heaton and Hilton Families, id45086 (Sub-series 2, Folder 4)
  - Pictures and Portraits, 1826-1842; id45087 (Sub-series 3)
    - 1826-1942, id45088 (Sub-series 3, Folder 5)
      - John Holmes Offley, 1826; id45089 (Sub-series 3, Folder 5)
      - John Holmes Offley, 1842; id45090 (Sub-series 3, Folder 5)
      - David Offley, id45091 (Sub-series 3, Folder 5)
      - Catharine V.R.H. Offley, id45092 (Sub-series 3, Folder 5)
      - Smyrna, id45093 (Sub-series 3, Folder 5)
- J.M. Offley, 1916; id45094
  - Diary, 1916; id45095 (Folder 6)
- R.S. Offley, 1891-1900; id45096
  - Military Documentation, 1891-1900; id45097 (Sub-series 1)
    - 1891-1900, id45098 (Sub-series 1, Folder 7)
      - Membership Card, id45099 (Sub-series 1, Folder 7)
      - Order, September 17, 1891; id45100 (Sub-series 1, Folder 7)
      - Order, May 25, 1900; id45101 (Sub-series 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1898; id45102 (Sub-series 2)
    - November 18, 1898, id45103 (Sub-series 2, Folder 8)
- C.N. Offley, 1898; id45104
  - Written Account, 1898; id45105 (Sub-series 1)
    - Battle of Santiago de Cuba, July 7, 1898; id45106 (Sub-series 1, Folder 9)
  - Photograph, 1898; id45107 (Sub-series 2)
    - C.N. Offley, 1898; id45108 (Sub-series 2, Folder 10)
- E.M. Offley, 1899-1916; id45109
  - Correspondences, 1906-1915; id45110 (Sub-series 1)
    - May 1906- May 1908, id45111 (Sub-series 1, Folder 11)
    - May 1908- November 1908, id45112 (Sub-series 1, Folder 12)
    - November 1908- April 1909, id45113 (Sub-series 1, Folder 13)
    - May 1909- September 1909, id45114 (Sub-series 1, Folder 14)
    - September 1909-September 1915, id45115 (Sub-series 1, Folder 15)
  - Diaries, 1900-1901; id45116 (Sub-series 2)
    - 1900, id45117 (Sub-series 2, Folder 16)
    - 1901, id45118 (Sub-series 2, Folder 17)
    - id45119 (Sub-series 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1899-1916; id45120 (Sub-series 3)
    - 1909-1916, id45121 (Sub-series 3, Folder 19)
      - Identity Card, id45122 (Sub-series 3, Folder 19)
      - Christmas Program, 1916; id45123 (Sub-series 3, Folder 19)
      - Order, July 26, 1909; id45124 (Sub-series 3, Folder 19)
  - Photographs, 1899-1902; id45125 (Sub-series 4)
    - 1899-1902, id45126 (Sub-series 4, Folder 20)
      - E.M. Offley, 1899; id45127 (Sub-series 4, Folder 20)
      - Company G 1st U.S. Cavalry, 1899; id45128 (Sub-series 4, Folder 20)
      - E.M. Offley, 1902; id45129 (Sub-series 4, Folder 20)
      - Carter Hall, id45131 (Sub-series 4, Folder 20)
      - USS St. Louis, id45133 (Sub-series 4, Folder 20)
- Deborah H.R. Priestly, 1856-1861; id45134
  - Diary, 1856-1861; id45135 (Folder 21)
- L.P. Corr, 1911-1912; id45137
  - Diary, 1911-1912; id45138 (Folder 22)
- R.P. Hobson, 1906; id45139
  - Correspondence, December 22, 1906; id45140 (Folder 23)
- Young Family, id45141
  - Photographs, id45142 (Folder 24)
    - Robert West Young, id45143 (Folder 24)
    - Anne Robinson Young, id45144 (Folder 24)
    - Eliza Ann Moore Young, id45145 (Folder 24)
    - Kate Most Young, id45146 (Folder 24)
    - Nathaniel Young, id45147 (Folder 24)
    - Tapley West Young, id45148 (Folder 24)
- Cleland Kinloch Nelson, id45149
  - Photograph, id45150 (Folder 25)
- Herman Schreirer, id45151
  - Photographs, id45152 (Folder 26)
    - Mission of San Juan, id45153 (Folder 26)
    - Old Catholic Church, id45154 (Folder 26)
- Unknown Creator, id45155
  - Photographs, id45156 (Sub-series 1)
    - id45157 (Sub-series 1, Folder 27)
      - Guantanamo Renactment, id45158 (Sub-series 1, Folder 27)
      - Troops at Portsmouth, id45159 (Sub-series 1, Folder 27)
      - Troops at Portsmouth, id45160 (Sub-series 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous, id45161 (Sub-series 2)
    - id45162 (Sub-series 2, Folder 28)
      - Description of Christmas, id45163 (Sub-series 2, Folder 28)
      - Song Lyrics, id45164 (Sub-series 2, Folder 28)